<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A publike declaration· made by the united Protestant princes electors and other princes, states and lords, of the Holie Empire, thereby shewing for what causes and reasons, they are mooued to ioyne together in a straight vnitie and alliance, to aide and assist the princes electors of BrandenBurgh and the Palsgraue: in the possession of the dukedomes, countryes and dominions of Gulike, Cleaue, and Berge. Translated out of the Duch copie, printed at Amsterdam by Michael Colyn, ann. 1610</title>
            <author>Protestant Union (1608-1620)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103058</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838817</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838817</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3206</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01655)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3206)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 958:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A publike declaration· made by the united Protestant princes electors and other princes, states and lords, of the Holie Empire, thereby shewing for what causes and reasons, they are mooued to ioyne together in a straight vnitie and alliance, to aide and assist the princes electors of BrandenBurgh and the Palsgraue: in the possession of the dukedomes, countryes and dominions of Gulike, Cleaue, and Berge. Translated out of the Duch copie, printed at Amsterdam by Michael Colyn, ann. 1610</title>
                  <author>Protestant Union (1608-1620)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 9, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by William Stansby] for Iohn Budge, and are to be sold at his shop in Britanes Bursse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dutch original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Germany --  History --  Rudolf II, 1576-1612 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3206:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3206:1"/>
            <p>A PVBLIKE DECLARATION Made by the Vnited Proteſtant Princes <hi>Electors and other Princes, States and</hi> Lords, of the HOLIE <hi>EMPIRE,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thereby ſhewing for what cauſes and reaſons, they are mooued to ioyne together in a ſtraight Vnitie <hi>and Alliance, to Aide and Aſsiſt the Princes Electors</hi> of BRANDEN BVRGH and the <hi>PALSGRAVE:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Poſſeſſion of the Dukedomes, Countryes and Dominions of Gulike, Cleaue, and BERGE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the Duch Copie, printed at Amſterdam by</hi> MICHAEL COLYN, <hi>Ann.</hi> 1610.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> IOHN BVDGE, <hi>and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Britanes Burſſe.</hi> 1610.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3206:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3206:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>REASONS MOVING the vnited Proteſtants, Princes <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, and other Princes, Lords and</hi> States of the whole Empire, to ioyne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to aſſiſt the Prince Elector of Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg and the Palſegraue, in the poſſeſſions of the Dukedomes and Dominions of Gulicke, Cleaue and Berge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E the vnited Proteſtant Princes Electors, &amp; others &amp;c. ſend gréeting with all obedience, offer of ſeruice, friendſhip, fauor, and grace firſt to the Romane Emperours Maieſty, our moſt gratious Lord and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and to all other Chriſtian Potentates, Electors, Princes, Prelates, Earles, Lords, Knights, Cities, Townes, and to euery man both within and without the Dominion and Country of Germany, of what eſtate, quality or condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be, certifying the ſaid Emperours royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and all and euery one of them, according to their eſtates and qualitie.</p>
            <p>That although in this our natiue Countrey of Germany, by the conſent and agréement of the head, and particular members thereof, many wholeſome, good, and profitable ordinances, and among them alſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3206:3"/>a common and religious peace is eſtabliſhed; and for the better obſeruation and maintenance thereof here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, openly publiſhed and proclaimed: to this end ſpecially, that, not onely iuſtice, as the foundation of good Gouernement, but alſo inward loue, peace, and vnity might be vpheld and maintained; wherein the Emperors Maieſtie, as well as all Princes Electors, Princes and members of the holy Empire, openly and faithfully promiſed and bound themſelues together, That none of them, of what eſtate or quality ſoeuer they were, for any cauſe whatſoeuer: nor vpon any outward ſhew or ground that might be made or deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſhould or would make warre, trouble, moleſt, vex, robbe, ſpoile, ranſacke, beſiege, nor ſecretly conſpire or make aliances or compacts againſt any others of the ſaid State and holy Empire. And alſo that no man ſhould by force of armes diſpoſſeſſe, or violently take from any other, any of their poſſeſſions, hereditary or committed vnto them in cuſtody, whether they be Townes, Caſtles, Villages, Churches, Cloyſters, <hi>Cluyſen, Tinſen,</hi> Reuenues, Tenths, moueable or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable goods, Royalties, Juriſdictions, Rights, Signeories, Lordſhips, Toles, Waters, Medowes, or any other their propertie and lawfull Dominions, none excepted: nor once moue nor ſtir their Tenants and Subiects to riſe vp againſt them in armes, or to ſhew them any vnnaturall diſobedience: But that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man ſhould ſuffer each other to enioy and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe his owne peaceably and quietly, without any moleſtation or trouble, and by no meanes to endure that any man (ſubmitting himſelfe to law and iuſtice) ſhould by force be put from his right, nor any wayes impeached in his honour, priuiledge and fréedome (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there is ſufficient prouiſion made by former lawes concerning the points aforeſaid, againſt all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3206:3"/>thoſe that ſhall in any wiſe whatſoeuer doe contrary to the ſame) That then the townes of the holy Empire ſhould ioyne together, and by force of armes ayd, aſſiſt, helpe, defend and maintaine the parties or Townes, &amp;c. in their right, and withſtand the violence and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, by ſuch parties vſed, as ſeeke to doe contrary thereunto.</p>
            <p>But for that within certaine yeares forepaſt (as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſufficiently ſheweth) ſuch Statutes of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Empire (which truely in themſelues are very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, and made to a good end and purpoſe) and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the penalties therein ſet downe for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution thereof, are partly hardly taken and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtred, and partly obſtinately and wilfully broken and not obſerued: and that the parties grieued and oppreſſed are neyther aided, aſſiſted, comforted nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued, how earneſtly, ſubmiſſiuely and publiquely ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they haue ſued and complained: whereof hath enſued, that ſuch oppreſſions and miſdemeanours in the holy Empire, the longer, the more haue encreaſed: whereby vnleſſe prouident care be ſpecially had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, (if we ſhould any longer wincke thereat, and by Gods helpe, by our Aſſemblies and méetings together, not take ſome good and ſpéedy orders to ſtay and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the ſame) in the end certainely there would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue an vtter ouerthrowing, and ſubuerſion of all ſuch wholeſome Statutes and Ordinances, and of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon peace and tranquility of the holy Empire.</p>
            <p>We therefore in the name of Almighty God, for the maintenance and aduancement of his godly Maieſtie, the vpholding of iuſtice, and the furtherance of peace and vnity, haue already for certaine yeares vnited and ioyned our ſelues together, thereby to intertaine a greater, néerer and faithfuller combination and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of friendſhippe; and that in no ſort, nor by no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3206:4"/>meanes, to the hinderance or moleſtation of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Emperours Maieſtie, our moſt gratious Lord and Soueraigne, to whom we are lawfully bound to ſhew all dutifull and ſubmiſſiue obedience, nor of any members of the Empire (that ſhew themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable vnto the Statutes and Ordinances afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) whereunto we all together, and euery one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, with all friendſhip, fauour, grace, and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourely good will are bound and obliged, nor alſo to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man in particular, and much leſſe to the breaking of any of the Conſtitutions of the ſaid holy Empire: but much rather for the maintenance thereof, and for the more aſſured vpholding of better peace, quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vnity, in ſuch manner and forme, as the like contracts and combinations of amity haue heretofore beene made and obſerued by our aunceſtors and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers of famous memory, in regard of the great loue and affection which they beare vnto their naturall Countrey.</p>
            <p>Therefore wee moſt humbly require and beſéech the Emperours Soueraigne Maieſtie, and all other Kings, Princes, Electors, Lordes, Knights, &amp;c. in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and euery one in particular, if it perchance (as we vnderſtand) his Maieſtie, or they ſhould be already perſwaded (by the meanes and deuiſes of turbulent, enuious, and vnquiet perſons) or hereafter might be ſeduced to beléeue, that ſuch our Aſſemblies and mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, were made, done or tended to the contempt or diſpiſing of the Imperiall Maieſtie, or for the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Romiſh Religion, or ſpecially for the diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulling, ſubuerting and preſent oppugning of ancient Iuriſdictions, to the great hinderance of Knights and Gentlemen, to whome the benefite and properties thereof, haue vntill this time belonged and appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: to take and draw them from them, and to put and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3206:4"/>turne them to their owne proper vſes. That it would pleaſe them not to giue any credite vnto any ſuch falſe and vntrue ſuggeſtions, and ſlaunderous calumniati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but rather to aſſure themſelues, that it is done by vs onely of méere and déere fidelity, loue, and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to our natiue Country, and for the maintenance of a peaceable eſtate; which (if it pleaſeth God) wee will in time make knowne, and manifeſt to the world; ſo that none that are or haue vnited themſelues with vs, ſhall haue cauſe to diſlike of our procéedings, but which is more, others both of the one and the other Religion ſhall haue cauſe, to vnite themſelues with vs, that ſo all hurtfull diſtruſt, hitherto had and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, may be taken away, and good and perfect vnity planted and vpholden.</p>
            <p>But we cannot refraine, but muſt let the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Maieſtie, and all other Potentates Electors, Princes and States, both within and without the Land; Vnderſtand, and be aduertiſed, That it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly and openly knowne vnto all men, how that after the death of the high and mighty Prince our friendly louing Vncle, couſin, brother in law, brother, and goſſip of famous memorie, <hi>Iohn William,</hi> Duke of Gulick, Cleaue and Bergh, Earle vander Marcke, Rauenſburgh and Moers, Baron of Rauenſten, and Chriſtmilder, in the right of the wiues of the Electors of Brandenburch, and the Palſgraue <hi>Philip Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> and of eyther of them by themſelues: the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Poſſeſſions of all the aforeſaid Duchies, Earle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and Baronies not <hi>clam</hi> or <hi>precario,</hi> but fréely, openly, and with the good wil of moſt of the Countries and Townes, is lawfully diſcended and fallen vnto them: and that with manifeſt proteſtation and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration by them made, that it is not done of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe or wrongfully to with-hold any man from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3206:5"/>being a Competitor therein if he hath any right there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, but that both the ſaid heires proteſt, touching the ſame, eyther for any part, or for the whole in generall; vnto euery man that will not deſiſt from their claime: before an vnpartiall Iudge, and in ſuch Townes and places, where the cauſe properly (and according to the authority of the holy Empire, and ſpecially of the Princes Electors) belongeth to be heard, to yéeld good ſufficient, and true reaſons and anſweres vnto them to maintaine their right; and which is more, if néede be, to giue ſufficient <hi>Cautio de iudicio ſiſti &amp; iudicatum ſolui,</hi> to proue their cauſe. And therfore we altogether ſéeke to foreſée and preuent that no man ſhall hinder nor moleſt them herein with vnlawfull power and forces, contrary to the Ordinances and Conſtitutions of the holy Empire.</p>
            <p>All this notwithſtanding, their proteſtations and lawfull right not once being conſidered nor reſpected, in the Emperours Court, and in the Emperours moſt Princely Maieſties Name and authority, it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and earneſtly practiſed and vndertaken <hi>de facto</hi> without due courſe of law and Iuſtice by power, and forcibly to diſpoſſeſſe and vtterly to expell the ſaid Princes, being lawfull heires thereunto, from the right and poſſeſſion thereof. To the which end, not onely <hi>Leopoldus</hi> Arch-biſhop of Auſtria, and Biſhop of Stratſbourgh and Paſſauwe, ſuddenly and ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly firſt hath taken and entred into the town of Gulick, and the ſame hitherto holden and kept by force, but hath procéeded further, and ſeacute;eketh to ſeaze vpon, and forcibly to hold certaine Gentlemens houſes, vilages, and Schonſes lying thereabouts, and to inuade other neighbour townes and places next adiacent, to kéepe the ſubiects thereof from their due obedience, and threatning the Princes Electors the right heires and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3206:5"/>poſſeſſours thereof as alſo all thoſe, that with due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and fidelity ſubmit themſelues vnto them with the moſt vndeſerued paine and puniſhment of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt (although in ſuch a caſe neuer heard of before in the holy Empire) if they reſiſt him; all to the end (as it is manifeſtly made known and verified vnto vs) That theſe Countries may be vnburthened, freed and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>ex faucibus hereticorum,</hi> as the States of the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Auſburg (<hi>e diametro</hi> contrary to the religious peace) are falſly called.</p>
            <p>In regard therfore that our aforeſaid brethren and members with their Adherents (according to the force and power of the Lawes and Ordinances of the holy Empire, and for the peace of the Lawe) haue deſired ayde and aſſiſtance of vs, and therewithall proteſted, that their intent neuer was, nor yet is to oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt the moſt high and puiſſant Imperiall Maieſty, as being their gratious Lord and ſoueraigne Prince: And we diligently conſidering all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, cannot otherwiſe finde nor perceiue, but that they ſéeke and deſire the accompliſhing of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Imperiall Lawes of the holy Empire, as they themſelues for the defence of their right, in a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted pamphlet haue ſufficiently and truely declared: whereunto for breuitie ſake we referre you. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not likewiſe thinke, imagine, nor once be perſwaded, that the Emperours Imperiall Maieſtie taketh any pleaſure in, or is content to permit any ſuch diſorderly and vnlawful procéedings to haue their courſe againſt the ſaid Princes (ſpecially being well enformed of the equity of the cauſe) conſidering that their capitulation ſpecifieth and containeth in it, that his Maieſtie is bound in all caſes and by all the meanes hée can, to maintaine (not onely all the Princes Electors, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all Princely members of the holy Empire, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3206:6"/>Princes and States) in their dignities, honours, rights, priuiledges, powers and forces, and to ſuffer them fréely to holde, poſſeſſe and inioy them, and for his owne part not to doe any thing to the contrary, nor yet to ſuffer nor endure the ſame to be done by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whatſoeuer. And alſo if his Maieſtie or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whatſoeuer had any thing to ſay vnto the Princes Electors, Princes, and States aforeſaid, or any intent to doe any ſuch thing; that (to ceaſe all vprores, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and other Controuerſies in the holy Empire, to maintaine peace and vnity therein) he ſhould ſuffer and permit them altogether &amp; euery one particularly, to be heard, and haue their cauſes adiudged before lawfull Iudges, and in open Courts of Law; but by no means to permit them (in any ſuch or other cauſes, vnder any pretence, or any mans name whatſoeuer, whrein they may haue Iuſtice, and offer and ſubmit themſelues thereunto) to be robbed, taken, ranſomd, burnt, fought withall, beſieged, expoſed, or in any waies ouer-run, ſpoiled and forcibly handled.</p>
            <p>Therefore we haue thought it our dueties, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the faiths and fidelities, whereby one Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie (in ſuch like caſe) is bound and obliged to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and by the force and power of the foreſaid Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the holy Empire, to aide and aſſiſt our brè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and fellow members as obedient Princes Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Empire: but in no other maner, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery one may lawfully procéede in his right, touching the principall matter without hinderance, and that they procéede not vnduely with vnlawfull power, againſt the aforeſaid capitulation and Ordinances of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, but that they may be ſuffered peaceably in their poſſeſſion, and to enioy the benefite of the Law, for the due procéeding therein, as alſo without it (according to all equity) they ought to haue.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3206:6"/>
            <p>Therefore our friendly requeſt and motion vnto all Chriſtian Princes and Common-wealths, but ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to all the Princes Electors, Princes and States of the holy Empire, is, not to take this our defenſiue, and naturall due aſſiſtance and ayde giuen at this time (as procéeding from Chriſtian loue, fidelity and commiſeration, and of it ſelfe being reaſonable and very neceſſary) in any euill part, much leſſe to hinder the ſame, but rather to ſhew all further ance and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance therein, and to put too their helping hands, to the end that all the aforeſaid troubles may be ended, and a better, truer and vprighter concord be held and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, among the States of the holy Empire. Which we in generall, and euery one by himſelfe according to his eſtate in particular in the like caſes and oceaſions will requite and acknowledge to our powers.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
